<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<diagnostics xmlns="tag:textalign.net,2015:ns">
    <input-directories count="1">file:/Users/eeb4/Documents/GitHub/fv/TAN-2021/applications/Diff+/fv-source-chunk11</input-directories>
    <main-input-resolved-uris count="5">file:/Users/eeb4/Documents/GitHub/fv/TAN-2021/applications/Diff+/fv-source-chunk11/1818_fullFlat_C11.xml file:/Users/eeb4/Documents/GitHub/fv/TAN-2021/applications/Diff+/fv-source-chunk11/Thomas_fullFlat_C11.xml file:/Users/eeb4/Documents/GitHub/fv/TAN-2021/applications/Diff+/fv-source-chunk11/1823_fullFlat_C11.xml file:/Users/eeb4/Documents/GitHub/fv/TAN-2021/applications/Diff+/fv-source-chunk11/msColl_C11.xml file:/Users/eeb4/Documents/GitHub/fv/TAN-2021/applications/Diff+/fv-source-chunk11/1831_fullFlat_C11.xml</main-input-resolved-uris>
    <MIRUs-chosen count="5">file:/Users/eeb4/Documents/GitHub/fv/TAN-2021/applications/Diff+/fv-source-chunk11/1818_fullFlat_C11.xml file:/Users/eeb4/Documents/GitHub/fv/TAN-2021/applications/Diff+/fv-source-chunk11/Thomas_fullFlat_C11.xml file:/Users/eeb4/Documents/GitHub/fv/TAN-2021/applications/Diff+/fv-source-chunk11/1823_fullFlat_C11.xml file:/Users/eeb4/Documents/GitHub/fv/TAN-2021/applications/Diff+/fv-source-chunk11/msColl_C11.xml file:/Users/eeb4/Documents/GitHub/fv/TAN-2021/applications/Diff+/fv-source-chunk11/1831_fullFlat_C11.xml</MIRUs-chosen>
    <main-input-files-space-norm count="5">
        <unparsed-text xml:base="file:/Users/eeb4/Documents/GitHub/fv/TAN-2021/applications/Diff+/fv-source-chunk11/1818_fullFlat_C11.xml"
            xml:lang="en"
            grouping-key="en"
            sort-key="1818_fullFlat_C11"
            label="1818_fullFlat_C11"
            _orig-attr-names="xml:lang">&lt;xml xml:lang="en"&gt;CHAPTER V. &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p1"/&gt;C&lt;hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p1_hi1"/&gt;LERVAL&lt;hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p1_hi1"/&gt; then put the following letter into my hands.&lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p1"/&gt; &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p2"/&gt;&lt;ab sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p2_ab1"/&gt;&lt;hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p2_ab1_hi1"/&gt;To&lt;hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p2_ab1_hi1"/&gt; V. F&lt;hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p2_ab1_hi2"/&gt;RANKENSTEIN&lt;hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p2_ab1_hi2"/&gt;.&lt;ab eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p2_ab1"/&gt; &lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p2"/&gt;&lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p3"/&gt;“&lt;hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p3_hi1"/&gt;MY DEAR COUSIN&lt;hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p3_hi1"/&gt;,&lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p3"/&gt; &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p4"/&gt;“I cannot describe to you the uneasiness we have all felt concerning your health. We cannot help imagining that your friend Clerval conceals the extent of your disorder: for it is now several months since we have seen your hand-writing; and all this time you have been obliged to dictate your letters to Henry. Surely, Victor, you must have &lt;pb xml:id="F1818_v1_127" n="115"/&gt;been exceedingly ill; and this makes us all very wretched, as much so nearly as after the death of your dear mother. My uncle was almost persuaded that you were indeed dangerously ill, and could hardly be restrained from undertaking a journey to Ingolstadt. Clerval always writes that you are getting better; I eagerly hope that you will confirm this intelligence soon in your own hand-writing; for indeed, indeed, Victor, we are all very miserable on this account. Relieve us from this fear, and we shall be the happiest creatures in the world. Your father’s health is now so vigorous, that he appears ten years younger since last winter. Ernest also is so much improved, that you would hardly know him: he is now nearly sixteen, and has lost that sickly appearance which he had some years ago; he is grown quite robust and active.&lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p4"/&gt; &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p5"/&gt;&lt;pb xml:id="F1818_v1_128" n="116"/&gt;“My uncle and I conversed a long time last night about what profession Ernest should follow. His constant illness when young has deprived him of the habits of application; and now that he enjoys good health, he is continually in the open air, climbing the hills, or rowing on the lake. I therefore proposed that he should be a farmer; which you know, Cousin, is a favourite scheme of mine. A farmer’s is a very healthy happy life; and the least hurtful, or rather the most beneficial profession of any. My uncle had an idea of his being educated as an advocate, that through his interest he might become a judge. But, besides that he is not at all fitted for such an occupation, it is certainly more creditable to cultivate the earth for the sustenance of man, than to be the confidant, and sometimes the accomplice, of his vices; which is &lt;pb xml:id="F1818_v1_129" n="117"/&gt;the profession of a lawyer. I said, that the employments of a prosperous farmer, if they were not a more honourable, they were at least a happier species of occupation than that of a judge, whose misfortune it was always to meddle with the dark side of human nature. My uncle smiled, and said, that I ought to be an advocate myself, which put an end to the conversation on that subject.&lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p5"/&gt; &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p6"/&gt;“And now I must tell you a little story that will please, and perhaps amuse you. Do you not remember Justine Moritz? Probably you do not; I will relate her history, therefore, in a few words. Madame Moritz, her mother, was a widow with four children, of whom Justine was the third. This girl had always been the favourite of her father; but, through a strange perversity, her mother could not endure &lt;pb xml:id="F1818_v1_130" n="118"/&gt;her, and, after the death of M. Moritz, treated her very ill. My aunt observed this; and, when Justine was twelve years of age, prevailed on her mother to allow her to live at her house. The republican institutions of our country have produced simpler and happier manners than those which prevail in the great monarchies that surround it. Hence there is less distinction between the several classes of its inhabitants; and the lower orders being neither so poor nor so despised, their manners are more refined and moral. A servant in Geneva does not mean the same thing as a servant in France and England. Justine, thus received in our family, learned the duties of a servant; a condition which, in our fortunate country, does not include the idea of ignorance, and a sacrifice of the dignity of a human being.&lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p6"/&gt; &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p7"/&gt;&lt;pb xml:id="F1818_v1_131" n="119"/&gt;“After what I have said, I dare say you well remember the heroine of my little tale: for Justine was a great favourite of your’s; and I recollect you once remarked, that if you were in an ill humour, one glance from Justine could dissipate it, for the same reason that Ariosto gives concerning the beauty of Angelica—she looked so frank-hearted and happy. My aunt conceived a great attachment for her, by which she was induced to give her an education superior to that which she had at first intended. This benefit was fully repaid; Justine was the most grateful little creature in the world: I do not mean that she made any professions, I never heard one pass her lips; but you could see by her eyes that she almost adored her protectress. Although her disposition was gay, and in many respects inconsiderate, yet she paid the &lt;pb xml:id="F1818_v1_132" n="120"/&gt;greatest attention to every gesture of my aunt. She thought her the model of all excellence, and endeavoured to imitate her phraseology and manners, so that even now she often reminds me of her.&lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p7"/&gt; &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p8"/&gt;“When my dearest aunt died, every one was too much occupied in their own grief to notice poor Justine, who had attended her during her illness with the most anxious affection. Poor Justine was very ill; but other trials were reserved for her.&lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p8"/&gt; &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p9"/&gt;“One by one, her brothers and sister died; and her mother, with the exception of her neglected daughter, was left childless. The conscience of the woman was troubled; she began to think that the deaths of her favourites was a judgment from heaven to chastise her partiality. She was a Roman Catholic; and I believe her confessor confirmed &lt;pb xml:id="F1818_v1_133" n="121"/&gt;the idea which she had conceived. Accordingly, a few months after your departure for Ingolstadt, Justine was called home by her repentant mother. Poor girl! she wept when she quitted our house: she was much altered since the death of my aunt; grief had given softness and a winning mildness to her manners, which had before been remarkable for vivacity. Nor was her residence at her mother’s house of a nature to restore her gaiety. The poor woman was very vacillating in her repentance. She sometimes begged Justine to forgive her unkindness, but much oftener accused her of having caused the deaths of her brothers and sister. Perpetual fretting at length threw Madame Moritz into a decline, which at first increased her irritability, but she is now at peace for ever. She died on the first approach of cold wea&lt;pb xml:id="F1818_v1_134" n="122"/&gt;ther, at the beginning of this last winter. Justine has returned to us; and I assure you I love her tenderly. She is very clever and gentle, and extremely pretty; as I mentioned before, her mien and her expressions continually remind me of my dear aunt.&lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p9"/&gt; &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p10"/&gt;“I must say also a few words to you, my dear cousin, of little darling William. I wish you could see him; he is very tall of his age, with sweet laughing blue eyes, dark eye-lashes, and curling hair. When he smiles, two little dimples appear on each cheek, which are rosy with health. He has already had one or two little &lt;hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p10_hi1"/&gt;wives&lt;hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p10_hi1"/&gt;, but Louisa Biron is his favourite, a pretty little girl of five years of age.&lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p10"/&gt; &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p11"/&gt;“Now, dear Victor, I dare say you wish to be indulged in a little gossip concerning the good people of Geneva. The pretty Miss Mansfield has already &lt;pb xml:id="F1818_v1_135" n="123"/&gt;received the congratulatory visits on her approaching marriage with a young Englishman, John Melbourne, Esq. Her ugly sister, Manon, married M. Duvillard, the rich banker, last autumn. Your favourite schoolfellow, Louis Manoir, has suffered several misfortunes since the departure of Clerval from Geneva. But he has already recovered his spirits, and is reported to be on the point of marrying a very lively pretty Frenchwoman, Madame Tavernier. She is a widow, and much older than Manoir; but she is very much admired, and a favourite with every body.&lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p11"/&gt; &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p12"/&gt;“I have written myself into good spirits, dear cousin; yet I cannot conclude without again anxiously inquiring concerning your health. Dear Victor, if you are not very ill, write yourself, and make your father and all &lt;pb xml:id="F1818_v1_136" n="124"/&gt;of us happy; or——I cannot bear to think of the other side of the question; my tears already flow. Adieu, my dearest cousin.&lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p12"/&gt; &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p13"/&gt;“E&lt;hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p13_hi1"/&gt;LIZABETH&lt;hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p13_hi1"/&gt; L&lt;hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p13_hi2"/&gt;AVENZA&lt;hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p13_hi2"/&gt;.&lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p13"/&gt; &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p14"/&gt;“Geneva, March 18th, 17—.” &lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p14"/&gt;&lt;/xml&gt;</unparsed-text>
        <unparsed-text xml:base="file:/Users/eeb4/Documents/GitHub/fv/TAN-2021/applications/Diff+/fv-source-chunk11/Thomas_fullFlat_C11.xml"
            xml:lang="en"
            grouping-key="en"
            sort-key="Thomas_fullFlat_C11"
            label="Thomas_fullFlat_C11"
            _orig-attr-names="xml:lang">&lt;xml xml:lang="en"&gt;CHAPTER V. &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p1"/&gt;C&lt;hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p1_hi1"/&gt;LERVAL&lt;hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p1_hi1"/&gt; then put the following letter into my hands.&lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p1"/&gt; &lt;del sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_del1"/&gt;&lt;ab sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_del1_ab1"/&gt;&lt;hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_del1_ab1_hi1"/&gt;To&lt;hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_del1_ab1_hi1"/&gt; V. F&lt;hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_del1_ab1_hi2"/&gt;RANKENSTEIN&lt;hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_del1_ab1_hi2"/&gt;.&lt;ab eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_del1_ab1"/&gt; &lt;del eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_del1"/&gt;&lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p2"/&gt;“&lt;hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p2_hi1"/&gt;MY DEAR COUSIN&lt;hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p2_hi1"/&gt;,&lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p2"/&gt; &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p3"/&gt;“I cannot describe to you the uneasiness we have all felt concerning your health. We cannot help imagining that your friend Clerval conceals the extent of your disorder: for it is now several months since we have seen your hand-writing; and all this time you have been obliged to dictate your letters to Henry. Surely, Victor, you must have &lt;pb xml:id="F1818_v1_127" n="115"/&gt;been exceedingly ill; &lt;del sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p3_del1"/&gt;and this makes us all very wretched, as much so nearly as after the death of your dear mother.&lt;del eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p3_del1"/&gt; and this suspicion fills us with anguish. I perceive that your father &lt;del sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p3_add1_del1"/&gt;conceals&lt;del eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p3_add1_del1"/&gt; attempts to conceal his fears from me; but cheerfulness has flown from our little circle, only to be restored by a certain assuranance that there is no foundation for our anxiety. At one time My uncle &lt;del sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p3_del2"/&gt;was&lt;del eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p3_del2"/&gt; being almost persuaded that you were indeed dangerously ill, &lt;del sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p3_del3"/&gt;and&lt;del eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p3_del3"/&gt; could hardly be restrained from undertaking a journey to Ingolstadt. Clerval always writes that you are getting better; I eagerly hope that you will confirm this intelligence soon in your own hand-writing; for indeed, indeed, Victor, we are all very miserable on this account. Relieve us from this fear, and we shall be the happiest creatures in the world. Your father’s health is now so vigorous, that he appears ten years younger since last winter. Ernest also is so much improved, that you would hardly know him: he is now nearly sixteen, and has lost that sickly appearance which he had some years ago; he is grown quite robust and active.&lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p3"/&gt; &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p4"/&gt;&lt;pb xml:id="F1818_v1_128" n="116"/&gt;“My uncle and I conversed a long time last night about what profession Ernest should follow. His constant illness when young has deprived him of the habits of application; and now that he enjoys good health, he is continually in the open air, climbing the hills, or rowing on the lake. I therefore proposed that he should be a farmer; which you know, Cousin, is a favourite scheme of mine. A farmer’s is a very healthy happy life; and the least hurtful, or rather the most beneficial profession of any. My uncle had an idea of his being educated as an advocate, that through his interest he might become a judge. But, besides that he is not at all fitted for such an occupation, it is certainly more creditable to cultivate the earth for the sustenance of man, than to be the confidant, and sometimes the accomplice, of his vices; which is &lt;pb xml:id="F1818_v1_129" n="117"/&gt;the profession of a lawyer. I said, that the employments of a prosperous farmer, if they were not a more honourable, they were at least a happier species of occupation than that of a judge, whose misfortune it was always to meddle with the dark side of human nature. My uncle smiled, and said, that I ought to be an advocate myself, which put an end to the conversation on that subject.&lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p4"/&gt; &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p5"/&gt;“And now I must tell you a little story that will please, and perhaps amuse you. Do you not remember Justine Moritz? Probably you do not; I will relate her history, therefore, in a few words. Madame Moritz, her mother, was a widow with four children, of whom Justine was the third. This girl had always been the favourite of her father; but, through a strange perversity, her mother could not endure &lt;pb xml:id="F1818_v1_130" n="118"/&gt;her, and, after the death of M. Moritz, treated her very ill. My aunt observed this; and, when Justine was twelve years of age, prevailed on her mother to allow her to live at her house. The republican institutions of our country have produced simpler and happier manners than those which prevail in the great monarchies that surround it. Hence there is less distinction between the several classes of its inhabitants; and the lower orders being neither so poor nor so despised, their manners are more refined and moral. A servant in Geneva does not mean the same thing as a servant in France and England. Justine, thus received in our family, learned the duties of a servant; a condition which, in our fortunate country, does not include the idea of ignorance, and a sacrifice of the dignity of a human being.&lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p5"/&gt; &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p6"/&gt;&lt;pb xml:id="F1818_v1_131" n="119"/&gt;“After what I have said, I dare say you well remember the heroine of my little tale: for Justine was a great favourite of your’s; and I recollect you once remarked, that if you were in an ill humour, one glance from Justine could dissipate it, for the same reason that Ariosto gives concerning the beauty of Angelica—she looked so frank-hearted and happy. My aunt conceived a great attachment for her, by which she was induced to give her an education superior to that which she had at first intended. This benefit was fully repaid; Justine was the most grateful little creature in the world: I do not mean that she made any professions, I never heard one pass her lips; but you could see by her eyes that she almost adored her protectress. Although her disposition was gay, and in many respects inconsiderate, yet she paid the &lt;pb xml:id="F1818_v1_132" n="120"/&gt;greatest attention to every gesture of my aunt. She thought her the model of all excellence, and endeavoured to imitate her phraseology and manners, so that even now she often reminds me of her.&lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p6"/&gt; &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p7"/&gt;“When my dearest aunt died, every one was too much occupied in their own grief to notice poor Justine, who had attended her during her illness with the most anxious affection. Poor Justine was very ill; but other trials were reserved for her.&lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p7"/&gt; &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p8"/&gt;“One by one, her brothers and sister died; and her mother, with the exception of her neglected daughter, was left childless. The conscience of the woman was troubled; she began to think that the deaths of her favourites was a judgment from heaven to chastise her partiality. She was a Roman Catholic; and I believe her confessor confirmed &lt;pb xml:id="F1818_v1_133" n="121"/&gt;the idea which she had conceived. Accordingly, a few months after your departure for Ingolstadt, Justine was called home by her repentant mother. Poor girl! she wept when she quitted our house: she was much altered since the death of my aunt; grief had given softness and a winning mildness to her manners, which had before been remarkable for vivacity. Nor was her residence at her mother’s house of a nature to restore her gaiety. The poor woman was very vacillating in her repentance. She sometimes begged Justine to forgive her unkindness, but much oftener accused her of having caused the deaths of her brothers and sister. Perpetual fretting at length threw Madame Moritz into a decline, which at first increased her irritability, but she is now at peace for ever. She died on the first approach of cold wea&lt;pb xml:id="F1818_v1_134" n="122"/&gt;ther, at the beginning of this last winter. Justine has returned to us; and I assure you I love her tenderly. She is very clever and gentle, and extremely pretty; as I mentioned before, her mien and her expressions continually remind me of my dear aunt.&lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p8"/&gt; &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p9"/&gt;“I must say also a few words to you, my dear cousin, of little darling William. I wish you could see him; he is very tall of his age, with sweet laughing blue eyes, dark eye-lashes, and curling hair. When he smiles, two little dimples appear on each cheek, which are rosy with health. He has already had one or two little &lt;hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p9_hi1"/&gt;wives&lt;hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p9_hi1"/&gt;, but Louisa Biron is his favourite, a pretty little girl of five years of age.&lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p9"/&gt; &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p10"/&gt;“Now, dear Victor, I dare say you wish to be indulged in a little gossip concerning the good people of Geneva. The pretty Miss Mansfield has already &lt;pb xml:id="F1818_v1_135" n="123"/&gt;received the congratulatory visits on her approaching marriage with a young Englishman, John Melbourne, Esq. Her ugly sister, Manon, married M. Duvillard, the rich banker, last autumn. Your favourite schoolfellow, Louis Manoir, has suffered several misfortunes since the departure of Clerval from Geneva. But he has already recovered his spirits, and is reported to be on the point of marrying a very lively pretty Frenchwoman, Madame Tavernier. She is a widow, and much older than Manoir; but she is very much admired, and a favourite with every body.&lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p10"/&gt; &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p11"/&gt;“I have written myself into good spirits, dear cousin; yet I cannot conclude without again anxiously inquiring concerning your health. Dear Victor, if you are not very ill, write yourself, and make your father and all &lt;pb xml:id="F1818_v1_136" n="124"/&gt;of us happy; or——I cannot bear to think of the other side of the question; my tears already flow. Adieu, my dearest cousin.&lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p11"/&gt; &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p12"/&gt;“E&lt;hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p12_hi1"/&gt;LIZABETH&lt;hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p12_hi1"/&gt; L&lt;hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p12_hi2"/&gt;AVENZA&lt;hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p12_hi2"/&gt;.&lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p12"/&gt; &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p13"/&gt;“Geneva, March 18th, 17—.”&lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p13"/&gt; &lt;note sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_note1"/&gt;This letter ought to be re-written. &lt;note eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_note1"/&gt;&lt;!--2018-04-25 ebb: This collation unit is identical to the 1818 text (no changes in Thomas copy here).--&gt;&lt;/xml&gt;</unparsed-text>
        <unparsed-text xml:base="file:/Users/eeb4/Documents/GitHub/fv/TAN-2021/applications/Diff+/fv-source-chunk11/1823_fullFlat_C11.xml"
            xml:lang="en"
            grouping-key="en"
            sort-key="1823_fullFlat_C11"
            label="1823_fullFlat_C11"
            _orig-attr-names="xml:lang">&lt;xml xml:lang="en"&gt;CHAPTER V. &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p1"/&gt;C&lt;hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p1_hi1"/&gt;LERVAL&lt;hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p1_hi1"/&gt; then put the following letter into my hands.&lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p1"/&gt; &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p2"/&gt;&lt;ab sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p2_ab1"/&gt;“&lt;hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p2_ab1_hi1"/&gt;To&lt;hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p2_ab1_hi1"/&gt; V. F&lt;hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p2_ab1_hi2"/&gt;RANKENSTEIN&lt;hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p2_ab1_hi2"/&gt;.&lt;ab eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p2_ab1"/&gt; &lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p2"/&gt;&lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p3"/&gt;“&lt;hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p3_hi1"/&gt;MY DEAR COUSIN&lt;hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p3_hi1"/&gt;,&lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p3"/&gt; &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p4"/&gt;“I cannot describe to you the uneasiness we have all felt concerning your health. We cannot help imagining that your friend Clerval conceals the extent of your disorder: for it is now several months since we have seen your hand-writing; and all this time you have been obliged to dictate your letters to Henry. Surely, Victor, you must have &lt;pb xml:id="F1823_v1_134" n="115"/&gt;been exceedingly ill; and this makes us all very wretched, as much so nearly as after the death of your dear mother. My uncle was almost persuaded that you were indeed dangerously ill, and could hardly be restrained from undertaking a journey to Ingolstadt. Clerval always writes that you are getting better; I eagerly hope that you will confirm this intelligence soon in your own handwriting; for indeed, indeed, Victor, we are all very miserable on this account. Relieve us from this fear, and we shall be the happiest creatures in the world. Your father’s health is now so vigorous, that he appears ten years younger since last winter. Ernest also is so much improved, that you would hardly know him: he is now nearly sixteen, and has lost that sickly appearance which he had some years ago; he is grown quite robust and active.&lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p4"/&gt; &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p5"/&gt;&lt;pb xml:id="F1823_v1_135" n="116"/&gt;“My uncle and I conversed a long time last night about what profession Ernest should follow. His constant illness when young has deprived him of the habits of application; and now that he enjoys good health, he is continually in the open air, climbing the hills, or rowing on the lake. I therefore proposed that he should be a farmer; which you know, cousin, is a favourite scheme of mine. A farmer’s is a very healthy happy life; and the least hurtful, or rather the most beneficial profession of any. My uncle had an idea of his being educated as an advocate, that through his interest he might become a judge. But, besides that he is not at all fitted for such an occupation, it is certainly more creditable to cultivate the earth for the sustenance of man, than to be the confidant, and sometimes the accomplice, of his vices; which is &lt;pb xml:id="F1823_v1_136" n="117"/&gt;the profession of a lawyer. I said, that the employments of a prosperous farmer, if they were not a more honourable, they were at least a happier species of occupation than that of a judge, whose misfortune it was always to meddle with the dark side of human nature. My uncle smiled, and said, that I ought to be an advocate myself, which put an end to the conversation on that subject.&lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p5"/&gt; &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p6"/&gt;“And now I must tell you a little story that will please and perhaps amuse you. Do you not remember Justine Moritz? Probably you do not; I will relate her history, therefore, in a few words. Madame Moritz, her mother, was a widow with four children, of whom Justine was the third. This girl had always been the favourite of her father; but, through a strange perversity, her mother could not endure &lt;pb xml:id="F1823_v1_137" n="117"/&gt;her, and, after the death of M. Moritz, treated her very ill. My aunt observed this; and, when Justine was twelve years of age, prevailed on her mother to allow her to live at her house. The republican institutions of our country have produced simpler and happier manners than those which prevail in the great monarchies that surround it. Hence there is less distinction between the several classes of its inhabitants; and the lower orders being neither so poor nor so despised, their manners are more refined and moral. A servant in Geneva does not mean the same thing as a servant in France and England. Justine, thus received in our family, learned the duties of a servant; a condition which, in our fortunate country, does not include the idea of ignorance, and a sacrifice of the dignity of a human being. &lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p6"/&gt;&lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p7"/&gt;&lt;pb xml:id="F1823_v1_138" n="119"/&gt;“After what I have said, I dare say you well remember the heroine of my little tale: for Justine was a great favourite of yours; and I recollect you once remarked, that if you were in an ill humour, one glance from Justine could dissipate it, for the same reason that Ariosto gives concerning the beauty of Angelica—she looked so frank-hearted and happy. My aunt conceived a great attachment for her, by which she was induced to give her an education superior to that which she had at first intended. This benefit was fully repaid; Justine was the most grateful little creature in the world: I do not mean that she made any professions, I never heard one pass her lips; but you could see by her eyes that she almost adored her protectress. Although her disposition was gay, and in many respects inconsiderate, yet she paid the &lt;pb xml:id="F1823_v1_139" n="120"/&gt;greatest attention to every gesture of my aunt. She thought her the model of all excellence, and endeavoured to imitate her phraseology and manners, so that even now she often reminds me of her.&lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p7"/&gt; &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p8"/&gt;“When my dearest aunt died, every one was too much occupied in their own grief to notice poor Justine, who had attended her during her illness with the most anxious affection. Poor Justine was very ill; but other trials were reserved for her.&lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p8"/&gt; &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p9"/&gt;“One by one, her brothers and sister died; and her mother, with the exception of her neglected daughter, was left childless. The conscience of the woman was troubled; she began to think that the deaths of her favourites was a judgment from heaven to chastise her partiality. She was a Roman Catholic; and I believe her confessor confirmed &lt;pb xml:id="F1823_v1_140" n="121"/&gt;the idea which she had conceived. Accordingly, a few months after your departure for Ingolstadt, Justine was called home by her repentant mother. Poor girl! she wept when she quitted our house; she was much altered since the death of my aunt; grief had given softness and a winning mildness to her manners, which had before been remarkable for vivacity. Nor was her residence at her mother’s house of a nature to restore her gaiety. The poor woman was very vacillating in her repentance. She sometimes begged Justine to forgive her unkindness, but much oftener accused her of having caused the deaths of her brothers and sister. Perpetual fretting at length threw Madame Moritz into a decline, which at first increased her irritability, but she is now at peace for ever. She died on the first approach of cold weather, at &lt;pb xml:id="F1823_v1_141" n="122"/&gt;the beginning of this last winter. Justine has returned to us; and I assure you I love her tenderly. She is very clever and gentle, and extremely pretty; as I mentioned before, her mien and her expressions continually remind me of my dear aunt.&lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p9"/&gt; &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p10"/&gt;“I must say also a few words to you, my dear cousin, of little darling William. I wish you could see him; he is very tall of his age, with sweet laughing blue eyes, dark eye-lashes, and curling hair. When he smiles, two little dimples appear on each cheek, which are rosy with health. He has already had one or two little &lt;hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p10_hi1"/&gt;wives&lt;hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p10_hi1"/&gt;, but Louisa Biron is his favourite, a pretty little girl of five years of age.&lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p10"/&gt; &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p11"/&gt;“Now, dear Victor, I dare say you wish to be indulged in a little gossip concerning the good people of Geneva. The pretty Miss Mansfield has already &lt;pb xml:id="F1823_v1_142" n="123"/&gt;received the congratulatory visits on her approaching marriage with a young Englishman, John Melbourne, Esq. Her ugly sister, Manon, married M. Duvillard, the rich banker, last autumn. Your favourite schoolfellow, Louis Manoir, has suffered several misfortunes since the departure of Clerval from Geneva. But he has already recovered his spirits, and is reported to be on the point of marrying a very lively pretty Frenchwoman, Madame Tavernier. She is a widow, and much older than Manoir; but she is very much admired, and a favourite with every body.&lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p11"/&gt; &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p12"/&gt;“I have written myself into good spirits, dear cousin; yet I cannot conclude without again anxiously inquiring concerning your health. Dear Victor, if you are not very ill, write yourself, and make your father and all &lt;pb xml:id="F1823_v1_143" n="124"/&gt;of us happy; or——I cannot bear to think of the other side of the question; my tears already flow. Adieu, my dearest cousin.&lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p12"/&gt; &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p13"/&gt;“E&lt;hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p13_hi1"/&gt;LIZABETH&lt;hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p13_hi1"/&gt; L&lt;hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p13_hi2"/&gt;AVENZA&lt;hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p13_hi2"/&gt;.&lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p13"/&gt; &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p14"/&gt;“Geneva, March 18th, 17—. &lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p14"/&gt;&lt;/xml&gt;</unparsed-text>
        <unparsed-text xml:base="file:/Users/eeb4/Documents/GitHub/fv/TAN-2021/applications/Diff+/fv-source-chunk11/msColl_C11.xml"
            xml:lang="en"
            grouping-key="en"
            sort-key="msColl_C11"
            label="msColl_C11"
            _orig-attr-names="xml:lang">&lt;xml xml:lang="en"&gt;Ch V– 113 He then put the following letter into my hands. "To V. Frankenstien Geneva &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0057__Pt2__main__d2e11934"/&gt;Apri&lt;del eID="c56-0057__Pt2__main__d2e11934"/&gt; March 18&lt;shi rend="underline"&gt; &lt;/shi&gt;17— "My dear Cousin "I cannot describe to you the &lt;w ana="start"/&gt;uneasi ness&lt;w ana="end"/&gt; we have all felt concerning your health We cannot help imagining that your friend Clerval conceals the &lt;w ana="start"/&gt;extent&lt;w ana="end"/&gt; of your disorder, for it is now several months since we have seen your handwriting and all this time you have been obliged to dictate to Henry – Surely Victor you must have been very ill and this makes us very wretched as much so &lt;addSpan spanTo="#c56-0058.05"/&gt;nearly as after the death of your dear mother . My father was almost persuaded &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0058__main__d2e12028"/&gt;of this&lt;del eID="c56-0058__main__d2e12028"/&gt; that you were indeed dangerously ill, and could hardly be re st rained from undertaking a journey to Ingolstadt. &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0058__main__d2e12067"/&gt;I&lt;del eID="c56-0058__main__d2e12067"/&gt; &lt;del next="#c56-0058.02" sID="c56-0058__main__d2e12071"/&gt;but I entreated him not&lt;del eID="c56-0058__main__d2e12071"/&gt; &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0058__main__d2e12074"/&gt;to undertake it &lt;del eID="c56-0058__main__d2e12074"/&gt;&lt;del next="#c56-0058.03" rend="strikethrough" xml:id="c56-0058.02" sID="c56-0058__main__d2e12080"/&gt;because&lt;del eID="c56-0058__main__d2e12080"/&gt; &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0058__main__d2e12091"/&gt;for &lt;del eID="c56-0058__main__d2e12091"/&gt;&lt;del rend="strikethrough" xml:id="c56-0058.03" sID="c56-0058__main__d2e12100"/&gt;although&lt;del eID="c56-0058__main__d2e12100"/&gt; &lt;delSpan rend="vertical_line" spanTo="#c56-0058.04"/&gt;his health is better now tha n it has been since the death of My beloved Aunt, yet &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0058__main__d2e12121"/&gt;tha&lt;del eID="c56-0058__main__d2e12121"/&gt; the fatigue might have &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0058__main__d2e12136"/&gt;make him very ill&lt;del eID="c56-0058__main__d2e12136"/&gt; &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0058__main__d2e12139"/&gt;and&lt;del eID="c56-0058__main__d2e12139"/&gt; Clerval always wr i tes that you were getting better &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0058__main__d2e12161"/&gt;and&lt;del eID="c56-0058__main__d2e12161"/&gt; I &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0058__main__d2e12175"/&gt;arden&lt;del eID="c56-0058__main__d2e12175"/&gt; eagerly hope you will confirm thisintelligence soon in your own handwriting for indeed, indeed Victor we are all very &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0058__main__d2e12192"/&gt;uneasy&lt;del eID="c56-0058__main__d2e12192"/&gt; miserable on this account . Relieve us from this fear and we shall be the happiest creatures in the world.– My uncles health &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0058__main__d2e12211"/&gt;impro&lt;del eID="c56-0058__main__d2e12211"/&gt; is now &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0058__main__d2e12219"/&gt;well &amp;amp;&lt;del eID="c56-0058__main__d2e12219"/&gt; &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0058__main__d2e12222"/&gt;&lt;del eID="c56-0058__main__d2e12222"/&gt;vigorous that he appears ten years younger since last winter. Ernest also is so much &lt;w ana="start"/&gt;improved&lt;w ana="end"/&gt;, &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0058__main__d2e12243"/&gt;so &lt;del eID="c56-0058__main__d2e12243"/&gt;that you would hardly know him; he is now nearly sixteen you know and has &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0058__main__d2e12253"/&gt;quite&lt;del eID="c56-0058__main__d2e12253"/&gt; lost that sickly appearance that he had some years ago – he is quite well &amp;amp; &lt;shi rend="underline"&gt;hearty&lt;/shi&gt; if I &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0059__main__d2e12273"/&gt;y&lt;del eID="c56-0059__main__d2e12273"/&gt; may use that term for it is very expressive. "My uncle and I conversed &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0059__main__d2e12283"/&gt;the&lt;del eID="c56-0059__main__d2e12283"/&gt; last night a long time about what profession Ernest &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0059__main__d2e12303"/&gt;&lt;shi rend="underline"&gt;should be&lt;/shi&gt; &lt;del eID="c56-0059__main__d2e12303"/&gt;should follow . His constant ill health when young has deprived him of the habit of application and now that he enjoys good health &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0059__main__d2e12330"/&gt;we&lt;del eID="c56-0059__main__d2e12330"/&gt; he is continually in the open air &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0059__main__d2e12335"/&gt;on&lt;del eID="c56-0059__main__d2e12335"/&gt; climbing the hills or rowing on the lake. I, therefore, proposed that he shouldbe a farmer which you know cousin is a favourite scheme of mine –A farmer's is a very healthy &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0059__main__d2e12355"/&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;del eID="c56-0059__main__d2e12355"/&gt; happy life; and the least hurtful or rather the most benificial &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0059__main__d2e12360"/&gt;of any&lt;del eID="c56-0059__main__d2e12360"/&gt; profession. of any. My &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0059__main__d2e12377"/&gt;father&lt;del eID="c56-0059__main__d2e12377"/&gt; uncle had an idea of his being educated as an advocate, that through his interresthe might become a judge. But besides that he is not at all fit for such an occupation, it is certainly &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0059__main__d2e12416"/&gt;better&lt;del eID="c56-0059__main__d2e12416"/&gt; more &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0059__main__d2e12421"/&gt;honourable&lt;del eID="c56-0059__main__d2e12421"/&gt; creditable to &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0059__main__d2e12431"/&gt;to&lt;del eID="c56-0059__main__d2e12431"/&gt; cultivate the earth for the &lt;w ana="start"/&gt;sustenance&lt;w ana="end"/&gt; of man than &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0059__main__d2e12441"/&gt;it&lt;del eID="c56-0059__main__d2e12441"/&gt; to be the confid a nt &amp;amp; sometimes &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0059__main__d2e12459"/&gt;a helpmate&lt;del eID="c56-0059__main__d2e12459"/&gt; the accomplice of &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0059__main__d2e12471"/&gt;their&lt;del eID="c56-0059__main__d2e12471"/&gt; his vices; which is the employment &amp;amp; of a Lawyer. &lt;delSpan rend="strikethrough" spanTo="#c56-0059.05"/&gt;And if he should become a judge I said that &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0059__main__d2e12511"/&gt;rich&lt;del eID="c56-0059__main__d2e12511"/&gt; the occupation of a prosperous farmer if it were not a more honourable it was at least a happier employ ment than that of a judge, whose misfortune it was always to meddle with the dark side of human nature My uncle smiled and said that I &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0060__main__d2e12541"/&gt;ougt&lt;del eID="c56-0060__main__d2e12541"/&gt; ought to be an advocate myself; which put an end to the conversation on that subject And now I must tell you a little story that will please you. Do you not remember &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0060__main__d2e12560"/&gt;Ju&lt;del eID="c56-0060__main__d2e12560"/&gt; Justine &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0060__main__d2e12563"/&gt;Martin&lt;del eID="c56-0060__main__d2e12563"/&gt;? Moritz? Perhaps you do not I will therefore tell you her story in a few words. Mad. Martin her Mother was a widow with four children of whom &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0060__main__d2e12584"/&gt;this&lt;del eID="c56-0060__main__d2e12584"/&gt; Justine was the third. This girl had always been the &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0060__main__d2e12592"/&gt;favou&lt;del eID="c56-0060__main__d2e12592"/&gt; favourite of her father &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0060__main__d2e12599"/&gt;and&lt;del eID="c56-0060__main__d2e12599"/&gt; but thro an odd perversity her Mother &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0060__main__d2e12620"/&gt;never&lt;del eID="c56-0060__main__d2e12620"/&gt; could &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0060__main__d2e12626"/&gt;bear&lt;del eID="c56-0060__main__d2e12626"/&gt; not endure her and after the death of M. &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0060__main__d2e12643"/&gt;Martin&lt;del eID="c56-0060__main__d2e12643"/&gt; Moritz treated her very ill. My aunt observed this, and when Justine was &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0060__main__d2e12654"/&gt;ten&lt;del eID="c56-0060__main__d2e12654"/&gt; twelve years old prevailed on her mother to allow her to live at our house. &lt;addSpan hand="#pbs" next="#c56-0061.01" spanTo="#c56-0060.04"/&gt;The republican institutions of our &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0060__left_margin__d2e12686"/&gt;state&lt;del eID="c56-0060__left_margin__d2e12686"/&gt; country, have produced simpler &amp;amp; happier manners than those which prevail in the great monarchies that surround it. &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0060__left_margin__d2e12704"/&gt;Ju Whilst&lt;del eID="c56-0060__left_margin__d2e12704"/&gt; Hence there is less &lt;w ana="start"/&gt;dis &lt;addSpan hand="#pbs" spanTo="#c56-0061.02" xml:id="c56-0061.01"/&gt;tinction&lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0060__left_margin__d2e12722"/&gt;s&lt;del eID="c56-0060__left_margin__d2e12722"/&gt; &lt;w ana="end"/&gt;between the classes into which human beings have been divided, &amp;amp; the lower orders being neither so poor nor so despised are more refined &amp;amp; moral. A servant at Geneva does not mean the same thing as a servant in France or England —Justine &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0060__left_margin__d2e12764"/&gt;&lt;shi rend="underline"&gt;was&lt;/shi&gt; &lt;del eID="c56-0060__left_margin__d2e12764"/&gt;thus recieved into our family to learn the duties of a servant, which in our fortunate country does not include a &lt;w ana="start"/&gt;sacrifize&lt;w ana="end"/&gt; of the &lt;w ana="start"/&gt;dignity&lt;w ana="end"/&gt; of a human being. &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0060__main__d2e12806"/&gt;Where&lt;del eID="c56-0060__main__d2e12806"/&gt; &lt;delSpan rend="strikethrough" spanTo="#c56-0060.05"/&gt;she was taught all the duties of servant &amp;amp; was very kindly treated. I dare say that you now remember all about it, for Justine was a great favourite of yours, &amp;amp; I &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0060__main__d2e12827"/&gt;remember&lt;del eID="c56-0060__main__d2e12827"/&gt; recollect you once said, that if you were &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0061__main__d2e12845"/&gt;a&lt;del eID="c56-0061__main__d2e12845"/&gt; in an ill humour one glance from Justine, could &lt;w ana="start"/&gt;dissipate&lt;w ana="end"/&gt; it &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0061__main__d2e12859"/&gt;from&lt;del eID="c56-0061__main__d2e12859"/&gt; for the same reason that Ariosto gave concerning the beauty of Angelica:– she looked so frank hearted and happy. My Aunt &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0061__main__d2e12875"/&gt;was very fond of her which&lt;del eID="c56-0061__main__d2e12875"/&gt; &lt;del next="#c56-0061.05" rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0061__main__d2e12878"/&gt;caused&lt;del eID="c56-0061__main__d2e12878"/&gt; concieved an attachment for her, by which she was induced &lt;del rend="strikethrough" xml:id="c56-0061.05" sID="c56-0061__main__d2e12901"/&gt;her to&lt;del eID="c56-0061__main__d2e12901"/&gt; to give her an&lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0061__main__d2e12919"/&gt;d&lt;del eID="c56-0061__main__d2e12919"/&gt; education superior to that which she had at first intended . &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0061__main__d2e12944"/&gt;and she&lt;del eID="c56-0061__main__d2e12944"/&gt; This benefit was fully repaid; &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0061__main__d2e12953"/&gt;for&lt;del eID="c56-0061__main__d2e12953"/&gt; Justine was the most grateful little creature in the world. I do not mean that she made any professions–I never heard one pass her lips &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0061__main__d2e12965"/&gt;w&lt;del eID="c56-0061__main__d2e12965"/&gt; but you could see by her eye that she almost adored her protectress. Although very gay, and in many respects inconsiderate, yet she paid the greatest attention to every gesture of my Aunt– she thought her the &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0061__main__d2e12983"/&gt;miracle&lt;del eID="c56-0061__main__d2e12983"/&gt; model of all &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0061__main__d2e12995"/&gt;perfection&lt;del eID="c56-0061__main__d2e12995"/&gt; excellence, and endeavoured to &lt;w ana="start"/&gt;imitate&lt;w ana="end"/&gt; her words and even her &lt;w ana="start"/&gt;manners&lt;w ana="end"/&gt;, so that even now she &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0061__main__d2e13029"/&gt;very&lt;del eID="c56-0061__main__d2e13029"/&gt; often &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0061__main__d2e13034"/&gt;puts&lt;del eID="c56-0061__main__d2e13034"/&gt; reminds me &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0061__main__d2e13050"/&gt;in mind&lt;del eID="c56-0061__main__d2e13050"/&gt; of her. &lt;delSpan rend="vertical_line" spanTo="#c56-0061.07"/&gt;&lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0061__main__d2e13055"/&gt;You did not&lt;del eID="c56-0061__main__d2e13055"/&gt; observe all this, nor did I at the time but it struck me afterwards when I reflected on the subject. When my dearest Aunt died every one was too much occupied in their own &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0062__main__d2e13083"/&gt;grif&lt;del eID="c56-0062__main__d2e13083"/&gt; grief to notice poor Justine who had attended her during her &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0062__main__d2e13088"/&gt;whole&lt;del eID="c56-0062__main__d2e13088"/&gt; illness with the greatest affection. Poor Justine was very ill but other tryals were reserved for her. One by one her brothers &amp;amp; sister had died and her mother was now with the exception of her neglected daugher &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0062__main__d2e13109"/&gt;was&lt;del eID="c56-0062__main__d2e13109"/&gt; left childless. The conscience of the woman was troubled and she began to think that the deaths of her favourites was a judgement sentfrom heaven to &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0062__main__d2e13126"/&gt;punish&lt;del eID="c56-0062__main__d2e13126"/&gt; chastise her partialli t y she was a roman Catholic and I believe her confessor encouraged the idea which she had concieved. . &lt;w ana="start"/&gt;Accordingly&lt;w ana="end"/&gt;, a few Months after your &lt;w ana="start"/&gt;departure&lt;w ana="end"/&gt; for I ngolstadt, &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0062__main__d2e13181"/&gt;sh&lt;del eID="c56-0062__main__d2e13181"/&gt; Justine was called home by her repentant Mother. Poor girl she wept when she quitted our house she was much altered since the death of my aunt: grief had given soft n ess and a winning mildness to her manners which had before been remarkable for vivacity. Nor &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0062__main__d2e13208"/&gt;did&lt;del eID="c56-0062__main__d2e13208"/&gt; was her residence at her Mothers house of a nature to restore her gaiety. The poor &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0062__main__d2e13216"/&gt;fo&lt;del eID="c56-0062__main__d2e13216"/&gt; wo man was very vacillating in her repentance. She sometimes begged Justine to forgive her unkindness but much oftenor accused her as having caused the deaths of &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0063__main__d2e13237"/&gt;h&lt;del eID="c56-0063__main__d2e13237"/&gt; her brothers &amp;amp; sister. Perpetual fretting at last threw Mad. Martin into a decline, which at first encreased her irritability but she is now at rest for ever; &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0063__main__d2e13254"/&gt;for&lt;del eID="c56-0063__main__d2e13254"/&gt; &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0063__main__d2e13257"/&gt;&lt;del eID="c56-0063__main__d2e13257"/&gt;she &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0063__main__d2e13264"/&gt;did&lt;del eID="c56-0063__main__d2e13264"/&gt; died on the first approach of cold at the beginning of th is last winter &lt;delSpan rend="strikethrough" spanTo="#c56-0063.01"/&gt;that has just passed. Justine has returned to us and I assure you I love her tenderly. She is very clever and extremely mild &amp;amp; pretty and as I mentioned before &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0063__main__d2e13308"/&gt;she&lt;del eID="c56-0063__main__d2e13308"/&gt; &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0063__main__d2e13311"/&gt;is&lt;del eID="c56-0063__main__d2e13311"/&gt; her &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0063__main__d2e13316"/&gt;air&lt;del eID="c56-0063__main__d2e13316"/&gt; mein and her expressions &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0063__main__d2e13336"/&gt;are&lt;del eID="c56-0063__main__d2e13336"/&gt; continually remind me of my dear Aunt. &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0063__main__d2e13345"/&gt;And&lt;del eID="c56-0063__main__d2e13345"/&gt; I must say a few words to you also, My dear Victor, of little darling William. I wish you could see him. He is very tall of his age with sweet laughing blue eyes &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0063__main__d2e13357"/&gt;and&lt;del eID="c56-0063__main__d2e13357"/&gt; dark eyelashes and curling hair When he smiles two little dimples appear on his cheeks which are rosy with health — his chin comes down in a beautiful oval &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0063__main__d2e13369"/&gt;a&lt;del eID="c56-0063__main__d2e13369"/&gt; After this &lt;w ana="start"/&gt;description&lt;w ana="end"/&gt; I can only say what our visitors say a thousand times a day–'He is too pretty for a boy'. &lt;addSpan spanTo="#c56-0063.04"/&gt;He has already had one or two little &lt;shi rend="underline"&gt;wives&lt;/shi&gt; but Louisa &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0063__left_margin__d2e13411"/&gt;&lt;del eID="c56-0063__left_margin__d2e13411"/&gt;Biron is his favourite– a pretty little girl of five years old &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0063__main__d2e13439"/&gt;Miss Mansfeld&lt;del eID="c56-0063__main__d2e13439"/&gt; Now, dear Victor I dare say &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0064__main__d2e13452"/&gt;I&lt;del eID="c56-0064__main__d2e13452"/&gt; you wish to be indulged in a little gossip about your acquaintance. The pretty Miss Mansfeld has already received &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0064__main__d2e13462"/&gt;on&lt;del eID="c56-0064__main__d2e13462"/&gt; &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0064__main__d2e13465"/&gt;her&lt;del eID="c56-0064__main__d2e13465"/&gt; the congratulatory visits on her approaching marriage with a young Englishman, John &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0064__main__d2e13472"/&gt;Mebourne&lt;del eID="c56-0064__main__d2e13472"/&gt; &lt;w ana="start"/&gt;Melbourne&lt;w ana="end"/&gt; Esq. Her ugly sister Manon married M. Hofland the rich banker last autumn. Your favourite schoolfellow Louis Manoir &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0064__main__d2e13488"/&gt;ma&lt;del eID="c56-0064__main__d2e13488"/&gt; has suffered several misfortunes &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0064__main__d2e13494"/&gt;d&lt;del eID="c56-0064__main__d2e13494"/&gt; since the departure of Clerval from Geneva &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0064__main__d2e13499"/&gt;b&lt;del eID="c56-0064__main__d2e13499"/&gt; But he has &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0064__main__d2e13504"/&gt;atready&lt;del eID="c56-0064__main__d2e13504"/&gt; already recovered his spirits and he reported to &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0064__main__d2e13510"/&gt;m&lt;del eID="c56-0064__main__d2e13510"/&gt; be on the point of marrying a very lively pretty french woman— Mad. Tavernier –She is a widow and much older than Manoir but she is much &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0064__main__d2e13522"/&gt;adv&lt;del eID="c56-0064__main__d2e13522"/&gt; admired and a favourite with every body. I have written myself into good &lt;w ana="start"/&gt;spirits&lt;w ana="end"/&gt;, dear Cousin yet I can not conclude without again anxiously enquiring concerning your health— Dear Victor, if you are not very ill write yourself and make your father and all of us happy or— I cannot bear to &lt;addSpan spanTo="#c56-0064.02"/&gt;think on the other side of the question my tears &lt;w ana="start"/&gt;already&lt;w ana="end"/&gt; flow Your very affectionate Cousin &lt;del rend="strikethrough" sID="c56-0064__main__d2e13594"/&gt;dearrest&lt;del eID="c56-0064__main__d2e13594"/&gt; – dearest Victor Elizabeth Lavenza write– &lt;/xml&gt;</unparsed-text>
        <unparsed-text xml:base="file:/Users/eeb4/Documents/GitHub/fv/TAN-2021/applications/Diff+/fv-source-chunk11/1831_fullFlat_C11.xml"
            xml:lang="en"
            grouping-key="en"
            sort-key="1831_fullFlat_C11"
            label="1831_fullFlat_C11"
            _orig-attr-names="xml:lang">&lt;xml xml:lang="en"&gt;CHAPTER VI. &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p1"/&gt;C&lt;hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p1_hi1"/&gt;LERVAL&lt;hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p1_hi1"/&gt; then put the following letter into my hands. It was from my own Elizabeth:—&lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p1"/&gt; &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p2"/&gt;“My dearest Cousin,&lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p2"/&gt; &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p3"/&gt;“You have been ill, very ill, and even the constant letters of dear kind Henry are not sufficient to reassure me on your account. You are forbidden to write—to hold a pen; yet one word from you, dear Victor, is necessary to calm our apprehensions. For a long time I have thought that each post would bring this line, and my persuasions have restrained my uncle from undertaking a journey to Ingolstadt. I have prevented his encountering the inconveniences and perhaps dangers of so long a journey; yet how often have I regretted not being able to perform it myself! I figure to myself that the task of attending on your sick bed has devolved on some mercenary old nurse, who could never guess your wishes, nor minister to them with the care and affection of your poor cousin. Yet that is over now: Clerval writes that indeed you are getting better. I eagerly hope that you will confirm this intelligence soon in your own handwriting.&lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p3"/&gt; &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p4"/&gt;“Get well—and return to us. You will find a happy, cheerful home, and friends who love you dearly. Your father’s health is vigorous, and he asks but to see you,—but to be assured that you are well; and not a care will ever cloud his benevolent countenance. How pleased you would be to remark the improvement of our Ernest! He is now sixteen, and full of activity and spirit. He is desirous to be a true Swiss, and to enter into foreign service;&lt;pb xml:id="F1831_v_066" n="50"/&gt; but we cannot part with him, at least until his elder brother return to us. My uncle is not pleased with the idea of a military career in a distant country; but Ernest never had your powers of application. He looks upon study as an odious fetter;—his time is spent in the open air, climbing the hills or rowing on the lake. I fear that he will become an idler, unless we yield the point, and permit him to enter on the profession which he has selected.&lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p4"/&gt; &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p5"/&gt;“Little alteration, except the growth of our dear children, has taken place since you left us. The blue lake, and snow-clad mountains, they never change;—and I think our placid home, and our contented hearts are regulated by the same immutable laws. My trifling occupations take up my time and amuse me, and I am rewarded for any exertions by seeing none but happy, kind faces around me. Since you left us, but one change has taken place in our little household. Do you remember on what occasion Justine Moritz entered our family? Probably you do not; I will relate her history, therefore, in a few words. Madame Moritz, her mother, was a widow with four children, of whom Justine was the third. This girl had always been the favourite of her father; but, through a strange perversity, her mother could not endure her, and, after the death of M. Moritz, treated her very ill. My aunt observed this; and, when Justine was twelve years of age, prevailed on her mother to allow her to live at our house. The republican institutions of our country have produced simpler and happier manners than those which prevail in the great monarchies that surround it. Hence there is less distinction between the several classes of its inhabitants; and the lower orders being neither so poor nor so despised, their manners are more refined and moral. A servant in Geneva does not mean the same thing as a servant in France and England. Justine, thus received in our family, learned the duties of a servant; a condition which, in our fortunate country, does not include the idea of ignorance, and a sacrifice of the dignity of a human being.&lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p5"/&gt; &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p6"/&gt;“Justine, you may remember, was a great favourite of yours; and I recollect you once remarked, that if you were in an ill-humour, one glance from Justine could dissipate&lt;pb xml:id="F1831_v_067" n="51"/&gt; it, for the same reason that Ariosto gives concerning the beauty of Angelica—she looked so frank-hearted and happy. My aunt conceived a great attachment for her, by which she was induced to give her an education superior to that which she had at first intended. This benefit was fully repaid; Justine was the most grateful little creature in the world: I do not mean that she made any professions; I never heard one pass her lips; but you could see by her eyes that she almost adored her protectress. Although her disposition was gay, and in many respects inconsiderate, yet she paid the greatest attention to every gesture of my aunt. She thought her the model of all excellence, and endeavoured to imitate her phraseology and manners, so that even now she often reminds me of her.&lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p6"/&gt; &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p7"/&gt;“When my dearest aunt died, every one was too much occupied in their own grief to notice poor Justine, who had attended her during her illness with the most anxious affection. Poor Justine was very ill; but other trials were reserved for her.&lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p7"/&gt; &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p8"/&gt;“One by one, her brothers and sister died; and her mother, with the exception of her neglected daughter, was left childless. The conscience of the woman was troubled; she began to think that the deaths of her favourites was a judgment from heaven to chastise her partiality. She was a Roman catholic; and I believe her confessor confirmed the idea which she had conceived. Accordingly, a few months after your departure for Ingolstadt, Justine was called home by her repentant mother. Poor girl! she wept when she quitted our house; she was much altered since the death of my aunt; grief had given softness and a winning mildness to her manners, which had before been remarkable for vivacity. Nor was her residence at her mother’s house of a nature to restore her gaiety. The poor woman was very vacillating in her repentance. She sometimes begged Justine to forgive her unkindness, but much oftener accused her of having caused the deaths of her brothers and sister. Perpetual fretting at length threw Madame Moritz into a decline, which at first increased her irritability, but she is now at peace forever. She died on the first approach of cold weather, at the beginning of this&lt;pb xml:id="F1831_v_068" n="52"/&gt; last winter. Justine has returned to us; and I assure you I love her tenderly. She is very clever and gentle, and extremely pretty; as I mentioned before, her mien and her expressions continually remind me of my dear aunt.&lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p8"/&gt; &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p9"/&gt;“I must say also a few words to you, my dear cousin, of little darling William. I wish you could see him; he is very tall of his age, with sweet laughing blue eyes, dark eye-lashes, and curling hair. When he smiles, two little dimples appear on each cheek, which are rosy with health. He has already had one or two little &lt;hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p9_hi1"/&gt;wives&lt;hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p9_hi1"/&gt;, but Louisa Biron is his favourite, a pretty little girl of five years of age.&lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p9"/&gt; &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p10"/&gt;“Now, dear Victor, I dare say you wish to be indulged in a little gossip concerning the good people of Geneva. The pretty Miss Mansfield has already received the congratulatory visits on her approaching marriage with a young Englishman, John Melbourne, Esq. Her ugly sister, Manon, married M. Duvillard, the rich banker, last autumn. Your favourite schoolfellow, Louis Manoir, has suffered several misfortunes since the departure of Clerval from Geneva. But he has already recovered his spirits, and is reported to be on the point of marrying a very lively pretty Frenchwoman, Madame Tavernier. She is a widow, and much older than Manoir; but she is very much admired, and a favourite with everybody.&lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p10"/&gt; &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p11"/&gt;“I have written myself into better spirits, dear cousin; but my anxiety returns upon me as I conclude. Write, dearest Victor,—one line—one word will be a blessing to us. Ten thousand thanks to Henry for his kindness, his affection, and his many letters: we are sincerely grateful. Adieu! my cousin; take care of yourself; and, I entreat you, write!&lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p11"/&gt; &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p12"/&gt;“E&lt;hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p12_hi1"/&gt;LIZABETH&lt;hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p12_hi1"/&gt; L&lt;hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p12_hi2"/&gt;AVENZA&lt;hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p12_hi2"/&gt;.&lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p12"/&gt; &lt;p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p13"/&gt;“Geneva, March 18th, 17—.” &lt;p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p13"/&gt;&lt;/xml&gt;</unparsed-text>
    </main-input-files-space-norm>
</diagnostics>

